Let’s say you’re trying to
find some solid information
about a serious health
problem that concerns you,
like high blood pressure,
or diabetes.
Yet, everywhere you look,
someone’s trying to sell you
something like vitamins,
yoga mats, blenders, drugs.
Well, breathe a
sigh of relief
because all we bring
you are the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
When accompanied by a
strength-training regimen,
3 grams of creatine a day may improve
muscle performance in older adults.
Here’s our first story.
Creatine is a compound formed
naturally in the human body
that is primarily involved
in energy production
in our muscles and brain.
It’s also naturally formed
in the bodies of many animals we eat,
and so, when we eat
their muscles,
we can also take in some
creatine through our diet.
(It was named after kreas
the Greek word for “meat,”
in which it was first isolated.)
We need about two grams a day;
so, those who eat meat may get
like one gram from their diet,
and their body makes
the rest from scratch.
There are rare birth defects
where you’re born
without the ability to make it,
in which case you have to get it
all externally through diet.
But otherwise, our bodies can make
as much as we need to maintain
normal concentrations
in our muscles.
When people cut out meat,
the amount of creatine floating around
in their bloodstream
goes down,
but the amount in your brain
remains the same,
because your brain just makes
all the creatine it needs.
The level in vegetarian muscles
is lower,
but that doesn’t seem
to affect performance,
as both vegetarians and meat-eaters
respond to creatine supplementation
with similar increases
in muscle power output.
And if vegetarian muscle creatine
was insufficient,
then presumably they would have seen
an even bigger boost.
So basically, when you eat meat,
that just means your body
doesn’t have to make as much.
If creatine muscle content
dropped as we grew older,
that might help explain
age-related muscle loss,
but that doesn’t seem
to be the case.
Biopsies taken from the muscles
of young and old adults
show no difference
in creatine content.
Still, if it improves performance,
maybe it would help.
According to the International
Society of Sports Nutrition,
creatine monohydrate is the single most
effective ergogenic supplement
available to athletes
for increasing exercise capacity
and lean body mass
during training.
It’s no wonder surveys show
as many as 70+ percent
of collegiate athletes
have used creatine supplements.
What can it do for older adults?
Without exercise? Nothing.
Most studies on creatine supplementation
alone show no benefits
for muscle mass, strength,
or performance.
This makes sense,
given the mechanism.
Creatine supplementation
delays muscle fatigue.
This enables people to work out
longer and harder,
and it’s that additional
volume and intensity
that leads to the muscle benefits.
So, creatine alone doesn’t help,
and creatine taken in the context
of the same training
that’s carefully controlled
and deliberately equalized
doesn’t help either.
But let people exercise
as much as they can,
and most studies on creatine
supplementation
for the prevention
and treatment of sarcopenia
(meaning age-related muscle loss)
show augmented lean mass,
as it does in young adults.
Adding three to five grams
of creatine a day
to two to three days
of resistance training a week
added an additional three
extra pounds of lean mass
over an average duration
of about four months.
Now, some of that lean mass
may be water weight, not muscle.
Creatine causes water retention
that can show up as lean mass,
but compared to placebo, creatine
combined with resistance exercise
increases muscle strength as well.
And the additional gains in mass
and strength can persist
as long as 12 weeks after stopping
the creatine in older adults,
as long as the resistance
training is maintained,
so obviously, it’s not all
just water weight.
A reason I never advocated for creatine
supplementation in older adults
for muscle preservation
was because systematic reviews
up through 2017 concluded
that adding creatine to training
shows mixed results
for muscle mass and strength,
and it did not appear to translate
to improved functioning.
However, an updated meta-analysis
found a significant improvement
over placebo in sit-to-stand
test performance,
which is a decent predictor
of reduced falls risk.
Again, this was mostly only
when accompanied by strength training.
There have still been no consistent
benefits discovered
for just supplementing
with creatine alone.
So, creatine should always
be prescribed
with a progressive strength
training regimen.
The Society for Sarcopenia,
Cachexia, and Wasting Disease
convened an expert panel that,
despite the lack of long-term trials,
suggested creatine be indeed used
for the management of sarcopenia.
The recommended dose to achieve
muscle saturation is 3 grams a day.
Within a month at that slow
steady rate you achieve
the same muscle
levels as loading
with 120 grams over
a period of a week.
Note, though,
it takes at least 12 weeks
of creatine-supplemented
resistance training
to see a significant
additive effect.
Recent evidence suggests
taking it after exercise
might be slightly
preferable to before,
but this has yet to be verified.
Are there any side effects?
We’ll find out next.
The Society for Sarcopenia,
Cachexia, and Wasting Disease
convened an expert panel that,
despite the lack of long-term trials,
suggested creatine be used for the
management of age-related muscle loss,
also known as sarcopenia.
Are there any creatine side effects?
Well, if one can extrapolate from mice,
one side effect may be longevity.
The average healthy lifespan
of creatine-fed mice
was found to be 9 percent
more than control mice,
and they performed better
on neurobehavioral tests,
especially improved memory skills.
But is taking creatine safe?
One can take a bit of comfort in the fact
that it’s one of the world’s best-selling
dietary supplements, with literally
billions of servings taken,
and the only consistently reported
side effect has been weight gain,
presumed to be from water retention.
The only serious side-effects appear
to be among those with pre-existing
kidney diseases taking whopping doses
of like 20 grams a day for weeks.
The bottom line, according
to the European Food Safety Authority,
is that doses of up 3 grams a day
are unlikely to pose any risk
“provided high purity
creatine is used.”
Dietary supplements
are not regulated by the FDA
and may not actually contain
what’s on the label
or, in the case of creatine,
be tainted with contaminants
generated during the industrial
production process.
When researchers looked at 33 samples
of creatine supplements
made in the U.S. and Europe,
they all did actually contain creatine.
That’s good. But half exceeded
the maximum level recommended
by food safety authorities
for at least one contaminant.
The researchers recommend that consumers
choose products from producers
that ensure the “highest quality control,”
but that’s easier said than done.
One third party supplement testing outfit
that tested for purities
chose BulkSupplements brand
as their top pick,
which also happened to be the cheapest
at about 10 cents per daily 5 gram serving,
which is a level teaspoon.
What about just getting it from meat?
You could get those 3 grams of creatine
eating about five steaks a day,
since cooking destroys about 20 percent.
But the heat reacts with the creatine
and amino acids in meat
to create carcinogenic
heterocyclic amines,
one of the reasons meat
is considered to be cancer-causing.
A separate safety concern was raised
that creatine in supplement form
could potentially form
a different carcinogen
known as N-nitrososarcosine
when it hit the acid bath
of the stomach,
but when actually put to the test this
does not appear to be a problem.
Some have argued caution for creatine use
among those with kidney issues.
This concern appears to derive
in part from a misinterpretation
of laboratory data.
The blood levels of a different
compound called creatinine
is used as a marker
of kidney function.
It's a muscle metabolism waste product
that is regularly cleared out
by well-functioning kidneys;
so, if your levels rise, maybe
your kidneys aren’t doing so good.
But where does creatinine come from?
The breakdown of creatine.
So, if you take extra creatine,
your creatinine levels in your blood
could rise, giving the false impression
that your kidneys are malfunctioning,
but instead you’re just making more,
rather than clearing less.
For patients who take creatine, doctors
can consider other kidney function tests
such as blood levels
of cystatin C levels,
a waste product that's more independent
of dietary intervention.
So, tell your healthcare professional
if you start creatine.
Overall, creatine supplementation
appears to be safe for the kidneys,
but the longest study to date
is less than three years;
so, true long-term
studies are lacking.
Finally today,
what are the potential consequences of
having to make your own creatine
rather than relying
on dietary sources?
Almost universally, research findings
show a poor vitamin B12 status
among vegetarians because they're
not taking vitamin B12 supplements
like they should. And this results in
an elevation of homocysteine levels
that may explain why vegetarians
were recently found to have
higher rates of stroke.
Of course, plant-based eating is just
one of many ways to get B12 deficient.
I mean, even laughing gas can
do it, in as short as two days,
thanks to the recreational use
of whipped cream canister gas.
That's something new I learned today.
Anyways, if you do eat plant-based,
giving vegetarians and vegans
even as little as 50 micrograms
once a day of cyanocobalamin, the
recommended, most stable form
of vitamin B12 supplement,
and their homocysteine
levels start up in the elevated
zone, and within 1 to 2 months
their homocysteines normalize right
down into the safe zone under 10.
Or just 2000 micrograms of
cyanocobalamin once a week,
and you get the same beautiful
result, but not always.
In this study even 500 micrograms
a day, either as a sublingual chewable
or swallowable regular B12 supplement,
didn't normalize homocysteine
within a month. Now, presumably
if they had kept it up, their levels
would have continued to fall
like in the other study. But if you're
plant-based and have been taking
your B12 and your homocysteine levels
are still too high, meaning above 10,
is there anything else you can do?
Now, inadequate folate intake
can also increase homocysteine,
but folate comes from
the same root as foliage.
It's found in leaves, concentrated
in greens, as well as beans.
But if you're eating beans and
greens, taking your B12,
and your homocysteine level is still
too high, then I'd suggest trying,
as an experiment, taking
one gram of creatine a day
and getting your homocysteine levels
retested in a month to see if it helped.
Creatine is a compound formed
naturally in the human body
that is primarily involved in energy
production in our muscles and brain.
It's also naturally formed in the
bodies of many animals we eat.
And so when we eat their
muscles, we also can take in
some creatine through our diet.
We need about two grams a day,
so those who eat meat may get
like one gram from their diet, and
their body makes the rest from scratch.
There are rare birth defects where
you're born without the ability to make it,
in which case you have to get it
from your diet, but otherwise
our bodies make as
much as we need
to maintain normal
concentrations in our muscles.
When you cut out meat, the
amount of creatine floating around
in your bloodstream goes down, but the
amount in your brain remains the same,
showing dietary creatine doesn't
influence the levels of brain creatine,
because your brain just makes
all the creatine you need.
The level in vegetarian muscles is
lower, but that doesn't seem to affect
performance, as both vegetarians
and meat-eaters respond
to creatine supplementation with similar
increases in muscle power output.
And if vegetarian muscle
creatine was insufficient,
then presumably they would
have seen an even bigger boost.
So basically, all that happens
when you eat meat
is that your body just doesn't
have to make as much.
What does this all have
to do with homocysteine?
Okay, in the process of making creatine,
your body produces homocysteine
as a waste product. Now
normally this isn't a problem
because your body
has two ways to detoxify it
using vitamin B6 or using a
combination of vitamins B12 and folate.
Now B6 is found in both plant and
animal foods; it's rare to be deficient.
But B12 is mainly in animal
foods, and so can be too low
in those eating plant-based who don't
supplement or eat B12 fortified foods.
And folate is concentrated in plant
foods, so can be low in those
who don't regularly eat greens or
beans or folic-acid fortified grains,
and without that escape valve
homocysteine levels can get too high.
If, however, you're eating a healthy
plant-based diet and taking your B12
supplement, your homocysteine levels
should be fine, but what if they're not?
One might predict that if you started
taking creatine supplements,
the level of homocysteine might go
down since you're not going to have
to be making so much of it from scratch,
producing homocysteine as a by-product.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books were
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of “How Not to Age”.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.